Are you investigating this case as a serial murder?
이 사건을 연쇄살인으로 수사하시나요 ?
It's too early to confirm that.
그것을 확인하기에는 너무 이르다.
As you know,
아시다시피,
these murders took place in different districts.
이 살인은 다른 지역에서 일어났습니다 .
It's been over a month since the Suseong-dong incident.
수성동 사건이 발생한 지 한 달이 넘었다 .
You still haven't made any progress?
아직도 진전이 없나요?
The detectives in those districts and the Special Crime Squad
그 지역의 형사들 과 특수수사대
are doing their best.
최선을 다하고 있습니다.
Are you sure this isn't a serial murder?
이게 연쇄 살인이 아닌 게 확실한가요?
Everyone, please.
여러분, 부탁드립니다.
Don't jump to conclusions.
성급하게 결론을 내리지 마십시오.
You'll only scare the public.
대중에게 겁을 줄 뿐입니다.
I heard the MO for all three cases was the same.
세 사건 모두 MO가 동일하다고 들었습니다.
And your answer is still a no?
그런데 당신의 대답은 여전히 ​​'아니요'인가요?
Just look at these murders.
이 살인 사건을보세요.
Are you sure there weren't any accomplices?
공범자는 없는 게 확실해요 ?
Is there a reason behind not treating this as a serial murder?
연쇄살인으로 처리하지 않는 이유가 있나요 ?
Since the incidents took place in different districts,
사건은 다양한 지역에서 발생했기 때문에
they couldn't have been a one-man job.
그것은 한 사람의 일이 될 수 없었습니다.
You dropped this.
이걸 떨어뜨렸잖아
-I'm sorry. -Jeez.
-죄송합니다. - 이런.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Here it is.
여기있어.
Hello?
안녕하세요?
It's an alarm.
알람입니다.
Just last September,
지난해 9월
there were three break-ins that led to murders.
살인으로 이어진 침입 사건이 세 건 있었습니다 .
But the police still haven't found a suspect
그러나 경찰은 아직 용의자를 찾지 못했습니다
-Kitty, slow down. Okay? -which is alarming the public.
- 키티, 천천히 하세요. 좋아요? -대중을 놀라게 하고 있습니다.
The police announced that they are taking various approaches
경찰은 다양한 접근 방식을 취하고 있다고 발표
to investigate these three murder cases.
세 건의 살인 사건을 조사하기 위해
Some people are suggesting
몇몇 사람들이 제안하고 있습니다
that the culprit targeted wealthy senior citizens.
범인이 부유한 노인들을 표적으로 삼았다는 것입니다.
But the police stated that grouping individual cases into one serial case
그러나 경찰은 개별 사건을 하나의 연쇄 사건으로 묶는다고 밝혔습니다
was a risky move.
위험한 행동이었습니다.
-Without any definitive proof, -Take this.
-확실한 증거가 없으면 - 이것을 가져가세요.
-the police dispatched -What's that?
-경찰이 출동했습니다 - 그게 뭐죠?
more resources to question more people and focus more on legwork.
더 많은 사람들에게 질문 하고 발품 작업에 더 집중할 수 있는 더 많은 리소스
-But they haven't found a lead yet. -Okay.
-하지만 아직 단서를 찾지 못했습니다. - 알겠습니다.
The police are open to other possibilities
경찰은 다른 가능성을 열어두고 있습니다
such as robberies or crimes of passion by the victims' acquaintances.
피해자의 지인에 의한 강도나 정욕범죄 등
And the police are following up on other possibilities.
그리고 경찰은 다른 가능성에 대해서도 조사하고 있습니다 .
Listen. Detectives like us
듣다. 우리 같은 형사들
who do all the legwork catch the culprits.
모든 발품을 다하는 사람이 범인을 잡습니다.
When we were canvassing
우리가 조사를 하고 있었을 때
these neighborhoods to the point that we got blisters,
물집이 생길 정도로 이 동네는 요.
what did those district cops do?
그 지방 경찰들은 무엇을 했나요?
Yes. I'm glad you brought that up. Where were you in all of this?
예. 그 문제를 제기해주셔서 기뻐요. 이 모든 일에서 당신은 어디에 있었나요?
Right. You were at a sauna.
오른쪽. 당신은 사우나에 있었습니다.
I went there once!
나는 거기에 한 번 갔다!
Yes. I know that.
예. 나는 그것을 안다.
You went to the sauna once, the go club once,
사우나도 한 번, 바둑도 한 번,
and the Internet cafe once.
그리고 인터넷 카페도 한 번.
Are you having fun playing computer games with high schoolers when you're 40?
40대에도 고등학생들과 컴퓨터 게임을 하며 즐겁게 지내고 있나요 ?
Do you think she's the type to tell on people?
그녀가 사람들에게 말을 잘 하는 타입이라고 생각하시나요 ?
You punk. I have ears too.
이 새끼야. 나에게도 귀가 있다.
I think it's necessary to set boundaries between our squad and the Analysis Team.
우리 팀과 분석팀 사이에 경계를 설정하는 것이 필요하다고 생각합니다 .
Right. That's my point.
오른쪽. 그게 내 요점이야.
They just wear suits and act all cool.
그냥 정장만 입고 멋있게 행동하는 사람들이에요.
They just have meetings like some scholars.
그들은 단지 일부 학자들처럼 회의를 가질 뿐입니다 .
What do you think they can do?
그들이 무엇을 할 수 있을 것 같나요?
As long as they can pinpoint a suspect,
용의자를 특정할 수만 있다면,
it doesn't matter if they have meetings like scholars or standing on their heads.
학자들처럼 회의를 하든 , 머리 위에 서든 상관없습니다.
What do you care?
무슨 상관이야?
Entering the crime scene as they please is obstructing the investigation.
범죄 현장에 마음대로 들어가는 것은 수사를 방해하는 것입니다.
Captain Kook isn't Chief of Forensics anymore.
국 선장은 더 이상 법의학 책임자 가 아닙니다 .
And Song Ha-young was always into playing the hero.
그리고 송하영은 늘 주인공 역할에 푹 빠져 있었다.
He keeps crossing the line. You know how he is.
그는 계속 선을 넘고 있다. 그 사람이 어떤지 알잖아요.
I won't participate in making personal attacks.
나는 인신 공격에 참여하지 않을 것입니다.
What?
무엇?
Other teams aren't happy with the Behavioral Analysis Team.
다른 팀은 행동 분석 팀 에 만족하지 않습니다 .
If there are no boundaries between us and them,
우리와 그들 사이에 경계가 없다면 ,
whenever we get cases, there's bound to be conflict.
사건이 접수될 때마다 갈등이 생기기 마련이다.
Listen.
듣다.
They are taking the lead on their own.
그들은 스스로 주도권을 잡고 있습니다.
-How can I stop them? -Gosh.
-어떻게 막을 수 있나요? -맙소사.
Besides, they aren't really getting in your way.
게다가 그들은 실제로 당신을 방해하지도 않습니다.
They can actually help you out.
그들은 실제로 당신을 도울 수 있습니다.
Goodness. Did you all have coffee this morning?
선량. 오늘 아침 다들 커피 드셨나요?
-Hello, sir. -Hello.
-안녕하세요 선생님. -안녕하세요.
Come on! What's the matter with you?
어서 해봐요! 당신에게 무슨 문제가 있습니까?
What's going on in there?
거기 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는 거야?
It's too early to be yelling at this hour.
이 시간에 소리 지르기엔 너무 이르다.
Well, the thing is…
그런데 문제는???
Yesterday, when Chief Kim Bong-sik
어제 김봉식 실장 때
went to check out the area in Jinjung-dong,
진중동 지역을 둘러보러 갔는데
he ran into Inspector Song.
그는 송 경위를 만났습니다.
Darn it, that little…
젠장, 그거 좀???
Gosh.
이런.
-It's… -Captain Yoon and I
-그것은??? -윤 선장과 나
also run into him whenever we go to Suseong-dong or Gungok-dong.
수성동이나 군곡동에 가면 꼭 마주치는 사람이기도 합니다 .
It seems like Inspector Song is visiting all the scenes on a daily basis,
송 경위는 매일 모든 현장을 순찰하고 있는 것 같은데 ,
so people are talking.
그래서 사람들이 얘기를 해요.
-Captain Yoon. -Yes, sir.
-윤 선장. -알겠습니다.
As police officers, it is our job to catch criminals.
경찰관으로서 범인을 잡는 것이 우리의 임무입니다.
Whether he's trying to play a hero or not,
그가 영웅 역할을 하려고 하든 안 하든,
let's not doubt his genuine intentions.
그의 진정한 의도를 의심하지 말자.
I don't doubt his intentions.
나는 그의 의도를 의심하지 않습니다.
-Hello, sir. -What's going on?
-안녕하세요 선생님. -무슨 일이야?
The Behavioral Analysis Team reports directly to me.
행동분석팀이 저에게 직접 보고합니다.
What's your problem?
무엇이 문제입니다?
If you have a problem, talk to me.
문제가 있으면 나에게 이야기하세요.
It's not a big deal, sir. There was a misunderstanding.
별 일 아닙니다, 선생님. 오해가 있었습니다.
Ban the Analysis Team from entering the scenes.
분석팀의 현장 출입을 금지합니다.
Oh, that's what you want?
아, 그게 당신이 원하는 거예요?
That's it?
그게 다야?
Sure, fine.
물론이죠. 좋습니다.
If you have a problem with that,
그것에 문제가 있다면,
I'll be sure to let them know.
나는 그들에게 꼭 알려줄 것이다.
-Thank you, sir. -But the thing is,
-감사합니다. -근데 문제는,
I can't stop them if they want to conduct their own investigation.
그들이 스스로 조사를 하고 싶어도 막을 수가 없어요 .
They're cutting down on sleep to do that
그러기 위해 수면 시간을 줄이고 있어요
on top of conscientiously completing their own tasks,
자신의 임무를 성실하게 완수하는 것 외에도
so I can't tell them not to do that.
그래서 나는 그들에게 그렇게 하지 말라고 말할 수 없습니다.
I can't dictate how much sleep they get.
나는 그들이 얼마나 잠을 자는지 지시할 수 없습니다.
Right, they're not kids.
그렇죠, 그 사람들은 어린이가 아닙니다.
We're not asking you to just go ahead and stop them.
우리는 당신에게 그냥 가서 그들을 멈추라고 요구하지 않습니다 .
The Analysis Team needs to understand that they're not an investigation team.
분석팀은 자신들이 조사팀이 아니라는 점을 이해해야 합니다 .
Right, I also think…
그렇죠, 저도 그런 것 같아요???
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Hurry to the scene in Hwanghwa-dong.
황화동 현장으로 서둘러 가세요.
A senior citizen was murdered. Hurry to the scene at once.
노인이 살해당했습니다. 즉시 현장으로 달려가세요.
-Let's hurry. -Come on.
-서두르 자. -어서 해봐요.
Oh, I see. Got it.
알겠어요. 알았어요.
-It's urgent. -Okay.
-그것은 급해. -좋아요.
It's in Hwanghwa-dong!
황화동에 있어요!
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
-Hey, get the car ready! -Yes, sir!
-야, 차 준비해! -알겠습니다!
SEOUL METROPOLITAN POLICE AGENCY
서울지방경찰청
Gosh, I didn't know that so many people were into hiking.
맙소사, 하이킹을 좋아하는 사람들이 이렇게 많은지 몰랐어요 .
I did this all day yesterday, and I don't see an end in sight.
어제 하루종일 이 짓을 했는데 끝이 보이지 않네요.
I'll become a hiking expert at this rate.
이대로라면 나는 등산 전문가가 될 것이다.
Hey, those in Forensics have it way worse.
법의학 부서의 사람들은 상황이 훨씬 더 나쁩니다.
Their hands have already turned into feet,
그들의 손은 이미 발로 변했고,
so they walk on all fours now. Like this.
그래서 그들은 이제 네발로 걷습니다. 이와 같이.
Can't you laugh even if it's not funny?
재미없어도 웃을 수는 없나요?
Did he have to storm out like that?
꼭 그렇게 튀어나와야 했나요?
What would you like for lunch?
점심으로 무엇을 드시겠어요?
You've gotten quite brazen, Chu Chu.
꽤 뻔뻔해졌구나, 츄츄.
SPECIAL CRIME SQUAD 1
특수범죄수사대 1
Did something happen?
무슨 일 있었어?
Another senior citizen was murdered in Hwanghwa-dong.
황화동에서 또 다른 노인이 살해됐다 .
They all went to the scene a little while ago.
조금 전 모두 현장에 다녀왔습니다 .
Goodness. Hey! Get it done properly!
선량. 여기요! 제대로 끝내세요!
-Sir, you can't come in here. -Why not?
- 선생님, 여기 들어오시면 안 돼요. -왜 안 돼?
-Go the other way. -This is crazy.
-다른 길로 가세요. - 이건 미친 짓이야.
-Go the other way! -Darn it.
- 반대쪽으로 가세요! -젠장.
I didn't mean to offend you.
당신을 화나게 하려는 의도는 아니었어요.
I just said to go the other way. Gosh, this is so frustrating.
방금 다른 길로 가라고 했어요. 이런, 정말 실망스럽습니다.
Guys, keep the residents out.
여러분, 주민들을 쫓아내세요.
-Sir! You can't come in here. -Why not?
-선생님! 여기에 들어올 수 없습니다. -왜 안 돼?
This is nuts.
이건 미친 짓이야.
You can't come in here.
여기에 들어올 수 없습니다.
-You can't come in here. -Gosh. Move.
- 여기 들어오시면 안 돼요. -맙소사. 이동하다.
Gosh, what is this?
이런, 이게 뭐야?
Chief! You can't touch that. You know you can't touch anything here.
셰프! 당신은 그것을 만질 수 없습니다. 여기선 아무것도 건드릴 수 없다는 거 아시죠?
We're still trying to lift prints.
우리는 여전히 지문을 인양하려고 노력하고 있습니다.
-You can't touch that. -You can't come in here.
- 그거 만지면 안 돼요. - 여기 들어오시면 안 돼요.
-No, stop! -My goodness.
-멈추지 않음! -이럴 수가.
-Don't touch anything. -Darn it.
- 아무것도 만지지 마세요. -젠장.
-Get out. -Get rid of this stench first, idiot!
-나가세요. - 먼저 이 악취부터 없애라, 바보야!
-You're contaminating the scene. -Darn it. Let go!
- 현장을 오염시키고 있어요. -젠장. 가자!
Gosh.
이런.
-There he is. -Hey.
-저기요. -여기요.
Hey, how did the fire break out?
아, 어떻게 불이 났어요?
The culprit tried to set the house on fire.
범인은 집에 불을 지르려고 했다.
Thankfully, it died out after burning a part of the body and the ceiling.
다행히 몸 일부와 천장에 불이 붙은 뒤 사라졌다 .
Then maybe it was someone else.
그렇다면 다른 사람이었을 수도 있습니다.
We'd have to look into it further, but a blunt weapon was used.
좀 더 자세히 조사해 보아야 하는데 둔기가 사용된 것이었습니다.
The triangle again?
또 삼각관계야?
FORENSICS
법의학
Gosh, this is insane.
맙소사, 이건 미친 짓이야.
What is happening?
무슨 일이 일어나고 있나요?
Then why did he start the fire?
그렇다면 그는 왜 불을 지른 걸까요?
Maybe there was something he wanted to hide.
어쩌면 숨기고 싶은 것이 있었을지도 모릅니다 .
We're looking into that too.
우리도 그 점을 조사하고 있습니다.
I'll collect statements from the bereaved at the station.
역에서 유족들의 진술을 수집하겠습니다 .
Okay, sure.
그래, 물론이지.
How long will this take?
얼마나 걸릴까요?
There was a fire, so I'd say about ten hours.
불이 났으니 10시간쯤 걸렸을 것 같아요.
What's Kim Bong-sik doing inside?
김봉식 씨는 안에서 무엇을 하고 있나요?
I have no idea. Why is he…
나는 모른다. 그 사람은 왜???
I'll lift all his prints and submit them as evidence.
그의 지문을 모두 모아 증거로 제출 하겠습니다 .
-Darn it. -All right, I'm sorry.
-젠장. - 알았어, 미안해.
-Keep it up. -Get back to work.
-계속하세요. -일하러 돌아가세요.
-Thank you.
-감사합니다.
-What is going on? -Hey.
- 무슨 일이에요? -여기요.
-Gil-pyo. -Yes.
-길표. -예.
I told you not to smoke and contaminate the scenes.
담배를 피우 거나 현장을 오염 시키지 말라고 했어요 .
I'm just frustrated. They said it'd take ten hours.
나는 단지 좌절감을 느낀다. 10시간 정도 걸릴 거라고 하더군요.
Frustrated, my foot. How many of these did we find last time?
답답해, 내 발. 지난번에 우리가 이 중 몇 개를 찾았나요?
Do you want to end up on the list of suspects again?
다시 용의자 명단에 오르고 싶나요 ?
-Are you here to nag me or what? -Whatever. Anyway, what happened?
-나한테 잔소리 하러 온 거야, 아니면 뭐야? -무엇이든. 어쨌든, 무슨 일이 일어났나요?
It's being investigated now.
현재 조사 중입니다.
We're waiting too.
우리도 기다리고 있어요.
You guys in the Analysis Team should return to the office.
분석팀 여러분은 사무실로 돌아가세요.
-How can we return to the office? -Gosh, seriously.
-사무실로 돌아가려면 어떻게 해야 하나요? -맙소사, 정말요.
Captain Kook.
국 선장.
Chief Kim Bong-sik is inside.
안에는 김봉식 실장님이 계십니다.
He's inside?
그 사람 안에 있어요?
-Kim Bong-sik, this little… -Hey, stop.
-김봉식, 이거 좀??? -야, 그만해.
This is wrong.
이것은 잘못된 것입니다.
You're no longer in the Forensics Squad.
당신은 더 이상 법의학팀에 속하지 않습니다.
You know that Kim Bong-sik likes to talk.
김봉식 씨가 말하는 걸 좋아하는 거 아시죠?
Look, many eyes are watching.
보세요, 많은 눈들이 지켜보고 있습니다.
If people start to complain about your team frequenting the scenes,
사람들이 당신의 팀이 현장에 자주 방문하는 것에 대해 불평하기 시작하면 ,
things will get complicated for all of us.
상황은 우리 모두에게 복잡해질 것입니다.
Both you and Superintendent Baek are here.
당신과 백 교육감 모두 여기에 있습니다.
Why should I walk on eggshells around him?
왜 그 사람 주변의 달걀 껍질 위를 걸어야합니까?
We can't have your back forever.
우리는 영원히 당신의 등을 맡길 수 없습니다.
The two teams must respect each other's boundaries.
두 팀은 서로의 경계를 존중해야 합니다.
You were the one who came up with this system.
이 시스템을 생각해낸 사람은 바로 당신이었습니다 .
Exactly. Just go back to the office and wait.
정확히. 그냥 사무실로 돌아가서 기다리세요.
We'll share all the updates with you.
모든 업데이트를 여러분과 공유하겠습니다.
Why must we argue about this now?
왜 지금 우리가 이것에 대해 논쟁을 해야 합니까?
-Just go back to the office. -I'm so angry right now.
- 그냥 사무실로 돌아가세요. -나 지금 너무 화가 나.
Why is he standing there alone, looking all serious?
왜 그 사람은 진지한 표정으로 거기 혼자 서 있는 걸까요?
Let's go for a smoke.
담배 피우러 가자.
Sure, let's go.
물론이죠. 가죠.
-Go somewhere far. -I can smoke over there, right?
-먼 곳으로 가세요. -거기서 담배 피워도 돼요, 그렇죠?
-Not within a 50m-radius. -All right.
-반경 50m 이내는 아닙니다. -괜찮은.
-There must've been an arson attempt. -Yes, there's the burning smell.
-방화 시도가 있었나 봐요. - 네, 타는 냄새가 나요.
Who's the victim?
피해자는 누구입니까?
A female in her 60s.
60대 여성입니다.
A quiet alley in an affluent residential area.
부유한 주택가의 조용한 골목 .
I don't see a single security camera.
보안 카메라가 하나도 보이지 않습니다.
But an arson attempt. That's a first.
그러나 방화 시도. 그건 처음이에요.
It was premeditated, right?
미리 계획된 거였죠?
Yes. But something is off.
예. 하지만 뭔가 이상합니다.
What's odd?
무엇이 이상한가요?
The first incident took place on September 12.
첫 번째 사건은 9월 12일에 발생했다 .
The second one on the 24th. The third one on the 30th.
24일 두 번째. 30일 세 번째.
The interval between the cases has gone down from 12 to 6 days.
사건 간 간격이 12일에서 6일로 단축되었습니다.
But it has increased to a month.
그런데 한달로 늘었습니다.
If this really is a premeditated serial murder case,
만약 이것이 정말로 계획된 연쇄살인 사건이라면,
such decreased intervals and sporadic patterns
이러한 감소된 간격 과 산발적인 패턴
mean that the killer is becoming bolder.
살인자가 점점 더 대담해지고 있다는 뜻이다.
However, it took the killer a month to commit this murder.
그러나 살인자가 이 살인을 저지르는 데는 한 달이 걸렸다 .
There must've been a reason.
이유가 있었겠죠.
What could it be?
뭐가 될수 있었는지?
Was it suicide?
자살이었나요?
What caused the fire? Was it attempted arson?
화재의 원인은 무엇입니까? 방화를 시도한 걸까요?
-Move back. -Did the fire kill the victim?
-뒤로가. - 화재로 인해 피해자가 사망했나요?
-Or was it murder? -Move back!
- 아니면 살인이었나요? -뒤로가!
-Have you identified a suspect? -Yoon Tae-gu from Seoul HQ?
- 용의자를 특정했나요? -서울본사 윤태구?
There have been many murders lately. What's your plan?
최근에는 살인 사건이 많이 일어났습니다. 당신의 계획은 무엇입니까?
Was the victim murdered?
피해자가 살해됐나요?
Just a comment, please!
댓글 하나만 부탁드려요!
-What exactly happened? -Tell us!
- 정확히 무슨 일이 일어났나요? -말해보세요!
-Is this a homicide case?
-살인 사건인가요?
Earlier today, at around 11:10 a.m. on Thursday, October 30,
오늘 10월 30일 목요일 오전 11시 10분경
Yoon Jung-yoon, a 65-year-old female,
65세 여성 윤정윤 씨입니다.
was found dead in her home in Hwanghwa-dong, Seoul.
서울 황화동 자택에서 숨진 채 발견됐다 .
She was attacked with a blunt weapon.
그녀는 둔기로 공격을 받았습니다.
Her husband, Han Jong-yong,
남편 한종용씨.
saw that their house was filled with smoke
보니 그들의 집에 연기가 가득 찼더라
upon returning home from work
퇴근하고 집에 돌아오자마자
and called it in.
그리고 그것을 불렀습니다.
What was used to start the fire?
불을 피우는 데 무엇이 사용되었나요?
We believe that the culprit used
우리는 범인이 사용한 것으로 믿습니다
newspaper and paper to start the fire.
불을 피울 신문과 종이.
Any lead on the culprit?
범인에 대한 단서가 있나요?
We can't tell you anything at the moment.
지금은 아무 것도 말씀드릴 수 없습니다.
We're restricting access to the scene
현장 접근을 제한하고 있습니다
as we wait for the Forensics Squad's preliminary results,
포렌식스쿼드의 예비 결과를 기다리면서
so I hope you understand we can't share any details with you at the moment.
따라서 지금은 어떤 세부정보도 공유할 수 없다는 점을 이해하시기 바랍니다 .
Were any cash or valuables stolen from the scene?
현장에서 현금이나 귀중품이 도난당했나요 ?
How did she get in here?
그녀는 어떻게 여기에 들어왔나요?
At the moment,
현재,
it doesn't seem like anything was stolen.
아무것도 도난당한 것 같지 않습니다.
Do you still think it was done by an acquaintance of the victim?
아직도 피해자의 지인이 했다고 생각하시나요 ?
We are considering every possibility.
우리는 모든 가능성을 고려하고 있습니다.
As I mentioned earlier,
앞서 언급했듯이,
we're still waiting for the preliminary results--
우리는 아직 예비 결과를 기다리고 있습니다.
Do you admit that this may be connected to the cases
이 사건과 관련이 있을 수 있다는 점을 인정하시나요?
that occurred in Suseong-dong, Gungok-dong, and Jinjung-dong?
수성동, 군곡동, 진지동에서 일어난 일인가요?
Serial murders targeting affluent senior citizens.
부유한 노인을 겨냥한 연쇄살인 .
Do you admit it?
인정하시나요?
Well about that…
글쎄요???
We plan to expand the investigation keeping in mind
이를 염두에 두고 조사를 확대할 계획이다.
the possibility that the culprit could be the same person.
범인이 동일인일 가능성 도 있다.
Do you think there was an accomplice like the Jijon Family case?
지존씨 사건 같은 공범이 있었다고 생각하시나요 ?
There wasn't any accomplice?
공범은 없었나요?
Are they related?
관련이 있나요?
-Do you have any speculations? -Are the cases related?
-추측하는 부분이 있나요? -관련된 사건인가요?
Excuse me, reporters. I apologize.
죄송합니다, 기자님들. 사과드립니다.
I'm sure you have more questions,
더 궁금한 점이 있으실 거라 믿습니다.
but that's all for today's briefing.
오늘 브리핑은 이게 전부입니다.
We will do our best to arrest the culprit,
범인 검거에 최선을 다하겠습니다.
so please give us some time.
그러니 시간을 좀 주세요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
-Where are you going? -That's it?
-어디 가세요? - 그게 다야?
-Are those done by the same guy? -Is everything related?
-같은 사람이 만든 거야? -모든 것이 연관되어 있나요?
Breaking news.
속보.
This morning, a woman in her sixties was found dead
오늘 아침 60대 여성 숨진 채 발견
in a residential area in Hwanghwa-dong.
황화동 주거지역
The police launched an investigation.
경찰이 수사에 착수했습니다.
The police believe these cases of wealthy elderly murders
경찰은 부유한 노인 살인 사건을 믿고 있다
were possibly planned as serial murders.
연쇄살인으로 계획되었을 가능성이 있습니다.
The police identified the culprit of the Hwanghwa-dong incident
경찰이 황화동 사건의 범인을 지목했다
as the same one who committed the three previous murders of the elderly.
이전 세 번의 노인 살인을 저지른 사람과 동일합니다 .
They repeatedly stated they would expand the investigation
수사를 확대하겠다고 거듭 밝혔습니다
to a serial murder case.
연쇄살인사건
DAEHAN DAILY
대한데일리
POLICE ADMITS ELDERLY MURDERS AS SERIAL KILLING
경찰, 노인 살인을 연쇄 살인으로 인정
FORENSICS
법의학
Why did he suddenly start a fire?
왜 갑자기 불을 지른 걸까요?
He's never done that before.
그는 전에 그런 일을 한 적이 없습니다.
Did you find any inflammable?
가연성 물질을 찾았나요?
-Check out this area first. -All right.
- 먼저 이 부분을 확인해 보세요. -괜찮은.
He didn't prepare anything in particular.
그는 특별히 아무것도 준비하지 않았습니다.
I think it started with a newspaper.
아무래도 신문에서부터 시작됐던 것 같아요.
If he didn't bring any inflammable,
가연성 물질을 가져오지 않았다면,
I don't think he sought after
내 생각엔 그 사람이 추구한 게 아닌 것 같아
psychological exhilaration as most arsonists do.
대부분의 방화범이 그렇듯이 심리적인 흥분을 느낄 수 있습니다.
If he was after psychological exhilaration,
만약 그가 심리적인 흥분을 느끼고 있었다면 ,
he would've stayed and watched the fire grow.
그는 남아서 불이 커지는 것을 지켜봤을 것이다.
You're right.
네가 옳아.
I'm sure he came across an unexpected situation.
나는 그가 예상치 못한 상황에 직면했다고 확신합니다 .
He either wanted to destroy unwanted traces
그는 원치 않는 흔적을 파괴하고 싶었거나
or it could've been his trace.
아니면 그의 흔적이었을 수도 있습니다.
He failed to open the safe.
그는 금고를 열지 못했습니다.
Maybe this was a copycat crime.
아마도 이것은 모방 범죄였을 것입니다.
He wasn't keen on taking the valuables until now.
그는 지금까지 귀중품을 가져갈 생각이 없었습니다 .
But he used the same weapon.
하지만 그는 같은 무기를 사용했습니다.
Triangular?
삼각형?
Then let's check the body first.
그럼 먼저 본체를 확인해 볼까요?
He destroyed the cross.
그는 십자가를 파괴했습니다.
An unnecessary act.
불필요한 행위입니다.
Mallet. Hammer. Brick.
망치. 망치. 벽돌.
We took everything we could find
우리는 찾을 수 있는 모든 것을 가져갔습니다.
to see if any of them could leave a triangular mark,
그 중 삼각형 표시를 남길 수 있는지 확인하기 위해
but none of them did.
하지만 그들 중 누구도 그러지 않았습니다.
Do you think he made the weapon himself?
그 사람이 직접 무기를 만들었다고 생각하시나요?
The murder weapon?
살인무기?
I mean, we can't seem to find it.
내 말은, 우리가 그것을 찾을 수 없는 것 같다는 거죠.
His choice of a blunt weapon rather than a sharp one
날카로운 무기보다는 둔기 무기를 선택한 그의 선택
shows the anger built within the culprit.
범인의 내면에 쌓인 분노를 보여준다.
What made him become this furious
무엇이 그를 이렇게 격노하게 만들었나
to brutally kill complete strangers?
낯선 사람을 잔인하게 죽이려고?
-Let's check. -May I borrow a notebook?
-점검 해보자. -노트 좀 빌려도 될까요?
-Thank you. -First off, the front.
-감사합니다. -우선 앞면입니다.
One, two, three, four.
하나 둘 셋 넷.
On the head, one…
머리에 하나???
He isn't after money.
그는 돈을 추구하지 않습니다.
It wasn't done by an acquaintance who holds a grudge.
원한을 품고 있는 지인이 한 것이 아닙니다 .
In that case,
이 경우
where did his anger that ultimately made him attack
결국 그를 공격하게 만든 그의 분노는 어디로 갔는가
these helpless wealthy victims stem from?
이 무기력하고 부유한 피해자들은?
Are you sure?
확실합니까?
Last night,
지난 밤,
he wanted to put that jacket on, but he changed into something else,
그 재킷을 입고 싶었는데 다른 옷으로 갈아입었어요.
then left it on the sofa before he left.
그리고 그가 떠나기 전에 그것을 소파 위에 두었습니다.
But come morning,
그런데 아침이 되니,
the jacket was gone.
재킷이 없어졌습니다.
Maybe the victim moved it somewhere.
피해자가 어딘가로 옮겼을 수도 있습니다.
So I asked the chief of Forensics to find it first.
그래서 포렌식실장에게 먼저 찾아달라고 부탁했어요.
He looked for it twice, but it wasn't there.
그는 그것을 두 번 찾았 지만 거기에는 없었습니다.
He left the money and valuables.
그는 돈과 귀중품을 남겼습니다.
All he took was a black jacket?
그가 가져간 것은 검은색 재킷뿐이었다고?
It suddenly got chilly this morning.
오늘 아침 갑자기 추워졌어요.
This is such a shame.
정말 부끄러운 일입니다.
If we had cameras in the alleys, we would've found him by now.
골목에 카메라가 있었다면 지금쯤 그를 찾았을 겁니다.
We put up many more at the beginning of this year.
올해 초에는 더 많은 것을 올렸습니다 .
When we never had them, I never thought about it,
우리가 그것들을 갖지 못했을 때, 나는 그것에 대해 생각해본 적이 없었습니다.
but I guess I began to feel this way now that we have some.
하지만 이제 우리가 뭔가를 갖게 되면서 이런 느낌이 들기 시작한 것 같아요 .
They're making the control center next year.
내년에 통제 센터를 만들 예정이에요 .
Hopefully, things will change.
바라건대 상황이 바뀔 것입니다.
Over there.
저기요.
They're all wearing black.
다들 검은 옷을 입고 있어요.
But it's just a day's worth.
그러나 그것은 단지 하루의 가치입니다.
-Find someone in hiking boots. -Okay.
- 등산화를 신은 사람을 찾아보세요. -좋아요.
He carried a big weapon around, so I'll find someone with a backpack too.
그 사람이 큰 무기를 가지고 다니 니까 나도 배낭 메는 사람을 찾아볼게.
Once you screen them,
일단 선별해 보면,
ask the husband if it's the jacket he lost.
남편에게 잃어버린 재킷이냐고 물어보세요.
Yes.
예.
Goodness, Reporter Im Moo-sik.
맙소사, 임무식 기자.
I always gave you the information.
항상 정보를 주셨는데요.
If we find anything, I'll let you know first.
뭔가 발견하면 먼저 알려드릴게요.
Hey, wait.
어이 기다려.
Why? Did you find something?
왜요? 뭔가 찾으셨나요?
GUNGOK-DONG, HWANGHWA-DONG
궁곡동, 황화동
Man, look at this guy.
아저씨, 이 사람 좀 보세요.
SUSEONG-DONG, JINJUNG-DONG
수성동,진중동
-I'll call you back. -One second.
-다시 전화하겠습니다. -1초.
Gil-pyo!
길표!
-This jerk. -What? Did you find anything?
- 이 멍청이. -무엇? 뭔가 찾았나요?
Listen up.
잘 들어.
Suseong.
수성.
Gungok.
군고
Jinjung. Hwanghwa.
진중. 황화.
-What about them? -They have the same consonants.
- 그 사람들은요? -같은 자음이 있어요.
Darn it. Explain it so that I can understand.
젠장. 내가 이해할 수 있도록 설명해주세요.
Suseong. S and S.
수성. S와 S.
Gungok. G and G.
군곡. G와 G.
-Jinjung. -J and J.
-진중. -J와 J.
-Hwanghwa. -H and H!
-황화. -H와 H!
Look, they are all located in places with good access.
보세요, 모두 접근성이 좋은 곳에 위치해 있어요 .
Not only are there luxurious residential districts,
고급스러운 주거지역 뿐만 아니라 ,
but the towns also have a concentrated area of adult entertainment businesses
하지만 이 도시에는 성인 엔터테인먼트 사업이 밀집된 지역도 있습니다.
that are accessible by public transport.
대중교통으로 갈 수 있는 곳.
So what?
그래서 뭐?
The investigation team says he must've gone around in a car
조사팀은 차를 타고 돌아다녔던 것으로 추정
because he was never seen
왜냐하면 그는 한 번도 본 적이 없었기 때문이다
even though he committed the crimes in a large area.
넓은 지역에서 범죄를 저질렀음에도 불구하고 .
But it might be the opposite.
하지만 그 반대일 수도 있습니다.
Oh, he uses public transit?
아, 그 사람이 대중교통을 이용한다고요?
In-tak said there's a jacket missing, right?
인탁이가 자켓이 없다고 하더군요?
Yes, if that's true, it's another proof for our second theory.
예, 그것이 사실이라면 그것은 우리의 두 번째 이론에 대한 또 다른 증거입니다.
The temperature dropped this morning,
오늘 아침 기온이 뚝 떨어졌네요
so if he didn't have a car, he would've needed a jacket or something.
그러니 그에게 차가 없었다면 재킷 같은 것이 필요했을 것입니다.
We can make another assumption.
우리는 또 다른 가정을 할 수 있습니다.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
He could've needed to hide his bloodstained clothes.
그는 피 묻은 옷을 숨겨야 할 수도 있었습니다 .
If that's the case,
그렇다면,
then shouldn't we have many more witnesses?
그러면 증인이 더 많아야 하지 않겠습니까 ?
I mean, he used public transit.
내 말은, 그는 대중교통을 이용했다는 거야.
Even if he went around with bloodstained clothes,
피묻은 옷을 입고 돌아다녀도
most people wouldn't have noticed
대부분의 사람들은 눈치 채지 못했을 것입니다
unless they saw him near the crime scene.
범죄 현장 근처에서 그를 본 경우는 제외
Right, you're right.
그렇습니다. 당신 말이 맞습니다.
He wouldn't go around telling people he's a murderer.
그는 사람들에게 자신이 살인자라고 말하지 않았습니다 .
Also, surprisingly,
또한 놀랍게도,
people aren't too interested in others.
사람들은 다른 사람에게 그다지 관심이 없습니다.
Due to their inattentiveness,
그들의 부주의로 인해,
they wouldn't get suspicious nor perceive it as strange
그들은 의심하지도 않고 이상하다고 인식하지도 않을 것이다.
even if they saw his bloody clothes, just as Hwang Dae-sun said.
피묻은 옷을 보더라도 황대순의 말대로.
Right.
오른쪽.
GUNGOK-DONG, HWANGHWA-DONG, SUSEONG-DONG, JINJUNG-DONG
궁곡동, 황화동, 수성동, 진중동
RESTRICTED AREA AUTHORIZED PERSONNEL ONLY
제한 구역 승인된 직원만
That man. Is that the jacket?
그 사람. 그게 재킷인가요?
Hello?
안녕하세요?
Yes, Chief.
네, 국장님.
CHIEF OH IN-TAK OF FORENSICS
오인탁 포렌식 과장
To sum up, the culprit probably doesn't have a car,
정리하자면, 범인은 차가 없을 가능성이 높으며,
and he's a guy with a shoe size between 260mm to 265mm?
신발 사이즈가 260mm에서 265mm 사이인 남자인가요 ?
One second.
일초.
Hello, Captain Kook Young-soo of Behavioral Analysis…
안녕하세요, 행동분석 국영수 대위 ???
Hey, In-tak.
안녕, 인탁.
All right.
괜찮은.
Fax it over right away. Thanks.
즉시 팩스로 보내주세요. 감사해요.
We can stop looking for the shoes.
신발 찾는 걸 그만둬도 돼요.
They found it?
그들이 그걸 찾았나요?
-Which brand is it? -He'll fax it to me.
- 어느 브랜드인가요? - 그 사람이 나한테 팩스로 보낼 거야.
Wait, how does this make any sense?
잠깐, 이게 무슨 말이 되나요?
Why doesn't it? It fits perfectly.
왜 그렇지 않습니까? 완벽하게 맞습니다.
Have you found any evidence more trustworthy than this?
이보다 더 신뢰할 만한 증거를 발견하셨나요 ?
You should dispatch some men in Bangbae-dong.
방배동에 사람을 파견해야 합니다 .
You need to stop the fifth murder!
다섯 번째 살인을 막아야 한다!
You're all here. Take a look at this.
여러분은 모두 여기에 있습니다. 이것 좀 보세요.
-What? -You found something?
-무엇? - 뭔가 찾았나요?
The hiking shoes…
등산화???
Why do you have this?
왜 이것을 가지고 있습니까?
If you want to get cranky, you should do your job first.
짜증을 내고 싶다면 먼저 일을 해야 합니다.
I don't want any inconvenience either.
나 역시 어떤 불편함도 원하지 않는다.
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Darn it, the chief of Forensics is doing his job weirdly.
젠장, 과학수사과장이 일을 이상하게 하고 있군요.
Not as much as you, Chief.
당신만큼은 아니죠, 국장님.
-What? -You're with the superintendent.
-무엇? -당신은 교육감과 함께 있습니다.
-Okay. -Over here. This one.
-좋아요. -여기. 이 하나.
We found him.
우리는 그를 찾았습니다.
Yes, but you're a step too late.
그래요, 하지만 당신은 너무 늦었어요.
It's CCTV footage.
CCTV 영상이에요.
We got a shot of the back of the culprit.
범인의 뒷모습을 촬영했습니다.
What are we supposed to do with that?
그걸로 우리는 무엇을 해야 할까요?
We're still in a tight spot with or without leads.
우리는 단서가 있든 없든 여전히 빡빡한 상황에 처해 있습니다 .
We won't be able to find anything with that.
우리는 그것으로는 아무것도 찾을 수 없을 것입니다 .
Come to the conference room.
회의실로 오세요.
We caught the back of the culprit on a security camera.
범인의 뒷모습이 보안 카메라에 포착되었습니다.
Did you forget something?
뭔가 잊었나요?
-Should I go and fetch it now? -No. Wait.
-지금 가서 가져갈까? -아니요. 기다리다.
It's not his face. It's his back.
그의 얼굴이 아닙니다. 그의 등입니다.
Right. Yes.
오른쪽. 예.
Let's dispatch some people to Bangbae-dong.
방배동에 사람을 파견하자 .
And why don't we interrogate those with the same shoes in the area?
그리고 그 지역에서 같은 신발을 신고 있는 사람들을 심문해 보는 것은 어떨까요 ?
There will be countless people who own
소유한 사람은 셀 수 없이 많을 것이다.
the same hiking shoes of the same size just in Seoul.
서울에서만 같은 사이즈, 같은 등산화 .
We won't be able to track people who bought them in cash.
현금으로 구매한 사람들을 추적할 수 없습니다 .
We should start with the neighborhoods like we're taking a census.
인구 조사를 하는 것처럼 동네부터 시작해야 합니다 .
I think doing the legwork will be better.
다리 작업을 하는 것이 더 나을 것 같아요.
It's not just one neighborhood.
한 동네만 그런 게 아닙니다.
As you know, these murders took place all over Seoul.
아시다시피 이번 살인사건은 서울 전역에서 일어났습니다.
Sir, why are we going to Bangbae-dong?
선생님, 우리 방배동에 왜 가요?
What? Oh, that?
무엇? 아, 그거요?
All right. Listen up.
괜찮은. 잘 들어.
Suseong. Gungok.
수성. 껴안다.
Jinjung. Hwanghwa.
진중. 황화.
Anything?
아무것?
You idiots.
바보들아.
S and S. G and G.
S와 S.G와 G.
The syllables start with the same consonants.
음절은 동일한 자음으로 시작됩니다.
Let's put out an APB.
APB를 내보내자.
What nonsense is that?
그게 무슨 말도 안되는 소리야?
We must put out an APB.
APB를 설치해야 합니다.
How could we put out an APB with just that?
그것만으로 어떻게 APB를 내놓을 수 있겠습니까 ?
Come on in. You're here so join us.
들어오세요. 당신이 여기 있으니 우리와 함께 하세요.
And take us step by step.
그리고 우리를 한 걸음씩 나아가게 해주세요.
We must broadcast it nationally on the nine o'clock news.
9시 뉴스로 전국에 방송해야 합니다 .
He's driving me crazy. Come on.
그 사람이 나를 미치게 만들고 있어요. 어서 해봐요.
But we know nothing about the guy.
하지만 우리는 그 사람에 대해 아무것도 모릅니다.
You want us to do that with the footage that shows his back?
그의 등이 보이는 영상 으로 그렇게 하길 원하시나요 ?
Having the footage of his back won't make any difference.
그의 등을 촬영한 영상이 있어도 별 차이가 없습니다.
About 99 percent of the tips we receive won't be useful.
우리가 받는 팁의 약 99%는 유용하지 않습니다.
Then it will only complicate our investigation.
그러면 우리 조사가 더 복잡해질 뿐입니다 .
But while he keeps a low profile,
그러나 그는 낮은 프로필을 유지하는 동안
we can buy time.
우리는 시간을 살 수 있어요.
I think it's a good idea.
좋은 생각인 것 같아요.
The cooling-off period was long between the third and fourth cases because…
3번째와 4번째 사이에는 냉각기간이 길었습니다. 왜냐하면???
Wait. What's a cooling-off period?
기다리다. 냉각 기간이란 무엇입니까?
It's a hiatus for serial killers.
연쇄 살인범에게는 공백기입니다.
Hey, he didn't ask you.
이봐, 그 사람이 너한테 물어본 게 아니잖아.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
It took a month for him to commit the fourth murder
네 번째 살인을 저지르는 데 한 달이 걸렸다.
because of the press.
언론 때문에.
What about the press?
언론은 어떻습니까?
Up to the third case, his cooling-off period was shortened
3차까지는 쿨링오프 기간이 단축됐다.
because he was confident.
왜냐하면 그는 자신감이 있었기 때문이다.
-What's going on? -But the press
-무슨 일이야? -그러나 언론
raised suspicions of serial murder.
연쇄살인 의혹을 제기했습니다.
And they started to pay attention to each case individually.
그리고 그들은 각 사례에 개별적으로 주의를 기울이기 시작했습니다.
The moment he became confident,
자신감이 생긴 순간
he hesitated in case he might get caught.
그는 잡힐까 봐 망설였습니다.
But he killed again.
그런데 또 사람을 죽였습니다.
It means that the pleasure from killing
살인의 즐거움을 의미한다.
and his confidence overweighed his fear of getting caught.
그리고 그의 자신감은 잡힐 것에 대한 두려움보다 더 컸습니다.
You're saying that there could be another victim?
또 다른 피해자가 있을 수 있다는 말씀이신가요 ?
Yes. He only hesitated. He didn't stop.
예. 그는 단지 머뭇거릴 뿐이었다. 그는 멈추지 않았습니다.
Even if he kills again, it won't be easy to catch him.
또 사람을 죽인다고 해도 잡기가 쉽지 않죠.
That arrogant jerk.
그 오만한 놈.
Chief Kim Bong-sik.
김봉식 과장.
Do I have to teach you how to respect your colleagues?
동료를 존중하는 방법을 가르쳐야 합니까 ?
He's aware of his crimes
그 사람은 자신의 범죄를 알고 있어요.
and our investigation progress.
그리고 우리의 조사 진행 상황.
He's smart.
그는 똑똑해요.
Don't tell me you're buying this nonsense.
이런 말도 안되는 소리를 사고 있다고 말하지 마세요.
The culprit will watch the broadcast somewhere.
범인은 어딘가에서 방송을 볼 것이다.
-He pays attention to the press. -So…
- 언론에 주목하고 있다. -그래서???
are you suggesting that we give him a warning
우리가 그에게 경고를 하라고 제안하는 겁니까?
that he could get caught?
그 사람이 잡힐 수도 있다고?
That's correct.
맞습니다.
He has already committed four murders.
그는 이미 4번의 살인을 저질렀습니다.
He won't stop here.
그는 여기서 멈추지 않을 것이다.
The only way to prevent him from committing the next murder…
그가 다음 살인을 저지르는 것을 막는 유일한 방법은 ???
is this.
이것이다.
Stop him from striking again…
그 사람이 또 공격하는 걸 막으세요???
But we should consider this as making progress, right?
하지만 우리는 이것을 진전이 있는 것으로 생각해야 겠죠?
We found the hiking shoes.
등산화를 찾았습니다.
And we got his back on camera. I'm sure we'll find him soon.
그리고 우리는 그의 등을 카메라에 담았습니다. 곧 그를 찾을 수 있을 거라 확신해요.
Everyone is working together. He can't get away.
모두가 함께 일하고 있습니다. 그는 도망칠 수 없습니다.
You're right.
네가 옳아.
-Chu Chu, we'll give you a ride. -No. It's okay. I can take the bus.
-츄츄, 우리가 태워다줄게. -아니요. 괜찮아요. 버스를 탈 수 있어요.
-We have room. Let me drop you. -Yes.
-방이 있어요. 내가 당신을 떨어 뜨릴 수 있습니다. -예.
No. It's in a different direction.
아뇨. 다른 방향이에요.
Taking the bus is more comfortable.
버스를 타는 것이 더 편안합니다.
Okay. I get it. You want to get away from us as soon as possible.
좋아요. 알겠습니다. 당신은 가능한 한 빨리 우리에게서 벗어나고 싶어합니다 .
See you tomorrow.
내일 봐요.
-Okay. Goodnight. -Okay.
-좋아요. 안녕히 주무세요. -좋아요.
-Get home safely. -Goodnight.
- 집에 무사히 도착하세요. -안녕히 주무세요.
-Bye.
-안녕.
MURDER CASES IN SUSEONG-DONG, GUNGOK-DONG, AND JINJUNG-DONG
수성동, 궁옥동, 진중동 살인사건
MURDER CASE IN HWANGHWA-DONG
황화동 살인사건
Do you seriously believe putting out an APB will work?
APB를 설치하는 것이 효과가 있다고 진지하게 믿습니까 ?
Why not?
왜 안 돼?
With just that?
그것만으로?
You really should
당신은 정말로해야합니다
learn to listen to your colleagues.
동료의 말을 듣는 법을 배우십시오.
What?
무엇?
He wants to use this as a warning
그는 이것을 경고로 사용하고 싶어합니다
to stop the next murder.
다음 살인을 막기 위해.
I thought everyone understood that.
다들 그렇게 이해하는 줄 알았는데.
But I guess you didn't.
하지만 당신은 그러지 않았을 것 같아요.
A warning? As if.
경고? 마치.
Do you think our duty is to scare people?
사람들에게 겁을 주는 것이 우리의 의무라고 생각하시나요?
If you can't understand this,
만약 당신이 이것을 이해할 수 없다면,
following the majority is also a way.
다수를 따르는 것도 하나의 방법이다.
Hey.
여기요.
I've been too nice to you. How dare you talk to me like that?
나는 당신에게 너무 친절했습니다. 어떻게 감히 나한테 그런 말을 할 수 있어?
I really hope you will stop being nice to me.
나한테 좀 그만 친절하게 대해줬으면 좋겠어.
Your personality hasn't changed one bit. I bet you'll live a long life. Right?
당신의 성격은 조금도 변하지 않았습니다. 나는 당신이 오래 살 것이라고 확신합니다. 오른쪽?
What did you say?
뭐라고 하셨나요?
I'm your fellow detective.
나는 당신의 동료 형사입니다.
But you still treat me like a woman.
하지만 당신은 여전히 ​​나를 여자처럼 대해요.
Narrow-minded, shallow, biased, and immature.
마음이 좁고, 천박하고, 편견이 많고, 미성숙합니다.
That's how your perception is.
당신의 인식이 그렇습니다.
Gosh. You are also trying to ruffle up my feathers today.
이런. 너도 오늘 내 깃털을 헝클어뜨리려고 하는구나.
And are you cool with ruffling up other people's feathers?
그리고 다른 사람의 깃털을 휘젓는 것도 괜찮나요 ?
You little…
이 작은???
Did you see that?
그거 봤어?
If you weren't a woman,
여자가 아니었으면
I would have slapped you right away.
나는 즉시 당신을 때렸을 것입니다.
I'm not slapping you because you're a--
당신이--
This is my answer…
이게 내 대답이야???
to what you did to me before.
당신이 전에 나에게 한 일에 대해.
I thought I was over it.
나는 끝났다고 생각했다.
I guess I wasn't.
나는 그렇지 않았던 것 같다.
Hey, Yoon Tae-gu!
안녕하세요 윤태구님!
If you don't want to be treated like a woman,
여자대접받기 싫으면
cut your hair that you've insisted on growing for the victims!
피해자들을 위해 길러달라고 고집했던 머리를 잘라주세요 !
Darn it!
젠장!
So I pushed for it.
그래서 나는 그것을 추진했습니다.
Do you think putting out an APB will work?
APB를 설치하는 것이 효과가 있을 것이라고 생각하시나요?
If he hides, it will be harder to find him.
그가 숨어 있으면 그를 찾기가 더 어려울 것입니다.
You have a point.
당신은 요점이 있습니다.
But stopping the next murder is our top priority right now.
하지만 다음 살인을 막는 것이 지금 당장 우리의 최우선 과제입니다.
Right. That's true.
오른쪽. 그것은 사실이다.
Yes.
예.
Drop me off here.
나를 여기 내려주세요.
-Here? -Yes.
-여기? -예.
-Good work. -Thanks. Bye.
-잘 했어. -감사해요. 안녕.
-See you tomorrow. -Okay.
-내일 봐요. -좋아요.
Gosh.
이런.
-Captain Kook. -Yes?
-국 선장님. -예?
Hold on.
기다리다.
What?
무엇?
Wait. I have something.
기다리다. 나 무언 갈 가지고있어.
My mother gave it to me this morning. But I forgot about it all day. I'm sorry.
오늘 아침에 어머니가 나에게 그것을 주셨다. 그런데 하루종일 잊어버렸어요. 죄송합니다.
What is this? Why are you apologizing?
이게 뭔가요? 왜 사과하는 거야?
This is a present from me.
이것은 내가 주는 선물이다.
Happy birthday.
생일 축하해요.
Me? Today is…
나? 오늘은???
Goodness.
선량.
Hey, I'm an old man. I don't need presents.
안녕하세요, 저는 늙은이입니다. 선물은 필요하지 않습니다.
People in our line of work only memorize crime dates.
우리 업무에 종사하는 사람들은 범죄 날짜만 기억합니다.
We always forget birthdays.
우리는 항상 생일을 잊어버립니다.
Anyway, thank you.
아무튼 감사 해요.
And please thank your mother for me too.
그리고 어머니께도 감사 인사를 전해주세요.
-Sure. -You're making me blush.
-확신하는. -당신 때문에 얼굴이 붉어지네요.
-Gosh. Thanks. I mean it. -Sure.
-맙소사. 감사해요. 진심이야. -확신하는.
Okay.
좋아요.
Song Ha-young is a nice gifter.
송하영은 좋은 선물꾼이다.
Happy birthday to me.
생일 축하해요.
Oh, right.
아, 그렇죠.
Sorry, honey.
미안해, 내 사랑.
-I… -Happy birthday, honey.
-나??? -생일 축하해요, 여보.
-Happy birthday, Dad.
-생일 축하해요, 아빠.
-Happy birthday to you
-생일 축하합니다
-Happy birthday to you, dear Dad -Happy birthday to you, dear my husband
-생일 축하해요, 사랑하는 아빠 -생일 축하해요, 사랑하는 남편
-Happy birthday to you
-생일 축하합니다
-Goodness. Thank you. -Make a wish now.
-선량. 감사합니다. -지금 소원을 빌어보세요.
Dad, you need to make a wish.
아빠, 소원을 빌어야 해요.
Okay, hold on.
좋아요, 잠깐만요.
-Did you do it? -What did you wish for?
-당신이 그랬나요? -무엇을 원하셨나요?
It's a secret.
그것은 비밀.
-Come on.
-어서요. -어서.
I'm glad we got to wish you a happy birthday before midnight.
자정 이전에 생일 축하를 하게 되어 기쁘네요 .
I know. Thank you.
알아요. 감사합니다.
-I love you. -I love you, Dad.
-사랑해요. - 사랑해요, 아빠.
-And I miss you. -Me too. I love you too.
-그리고 당신이 그리워요. - 저도요. 나도 사랑해요.
Daddy's wish is…
아빠의 소원은???
But we know nothing about the guy.
하지만 우리는 그 사람에 대해 아무것도 모릅니다.
You want us to do that with the footage that shows his back?
그의 등이 보이는 영상 으로 그렇게 하길 원하시나요 ?
Having the footage of his back won't make any difference.
그의 등을 촬영한 영상이 있어도 별 차이가 없습니다.
About 99 percent of the tips we receive won't be useful.
우리가 받는 팁의 약 99%는 유용하지 않습니다.
Then it will only complicate our investigation.
그러면 우리 조사가 더 복잡해질 뿐입니다 .
Do you think putting out an APB will work?
APB를 설치하는 것이 효과가 있을 것이라고 생각하시나요?
If he hides, it will be harder to find him.
그가 숨어 있으면 그를 찾기가 더 어려울 것입니다.
Did we make the right decision?
우리가 올바른 결정을 내렸나요?
PROFILING REPORT ON SUSEONG, GUNGOK, JINJUNG, AND HWANGHWA CASES
수성, 궁곡, 진중, 황화 사건 에 대한 프로파일링 보고서
MURDER SUSPECT WANTED REWARD 50 MILLION WON
살인 용의자 수배 포상금 5천만원
What if this just ends up complicating our investigation?
이로 인해 조사가 복잡해 지면 어떻게 되나요 ?
-Send it right away. -I'm telling you. That's why.
- 바로 보내주세요. -내가 말하잖아. 그렇기 때문에.
We will put out an APB.
우리는 APB를 내놓을 것입니다.
Attention, please.
주의해 주십시오.
Hold on a moment.
잠깐만 기다려.
The phones will keep ringing off the hook.
전화벨이 계속 울리게 됩니다.
I know things will get hectic,
일이 바빠질 거라는 걸 알아요
but don't dismiss any info you obtain through these calls.
하지만 이러한 통화를 통해 얻은 정보를 무시하지 마십시오 .
If you hear anything suspicious, let us know.
의심스러운 소리가 들리면 알려주십시오.
Please remember that we must prioritize the calls from our tippers
팁 제공자의 전화를 우선적으로 처리해야 한다는 점을 기억하세요.
over the ones from the reporters.
기자가 보낸 것보다.
Now, back to your calls. I don't need your answer.
이제 통화로 돌아가세요. 나는 당신의 대답이 필요하지 않습니다.
Hello?
안녕하세요?
-Yes. -That's right.
-예. -좋아요.
-Yes, from now on… -Is that right?
-네, 이제부터??? - 그렇죠?
-As for the case… -I'll take care of that.
-사건은??? - 그건 제가 처리할게요.
The footage shows a man in a black jacket walking.
영상에는 검은 재킷을 입은 남자가 걷고 있는 모습이 담겨 있습니다.
He takes a look around, looking relaxed.
그는 여유로운 표정으로 주위를 둘러봅니다.
The police have identified the man in the footage
경찰은 영상 속 남성의 신원을 확인했습니다
as the prime suspect in the case.
사건의 주요 용의자로
The jacket he is wearing matches the one that is missing from the scene.
그가 입고 있는 재킷은 현장에서 사라진 재킷과 일치합니다 .
And he was caught on this camera immediately after the incident took place.
그리고 그는 사건 발생 직후 카메라에 포착됐습니다 .
According to the police, the size of this man's shoe print
경찰에 따르면 이 남자의 신발 자국 크기
matches that of the shoe print
신발 프린트와 일치
found at the scene of the senior citizen's murder.
노인 살해 현장에서 발견되었습니다 .
The MO seems similar as well,
MO도 비슷한 것 같아요,
so the possibility that the killer is the same person…
그럼 범인이 동일인일 가능성은 ???
How are you feeling? Better?
기분이 어때요? 더 나은?
Gosh, the commissioner was so mean to me.
아, 국장님이 나한테 너무 못되게 굴었어요.
-Gosh. -Last night,
-맙소사. -지난 밤,
when I went to his office to get his approval on the APB,
제가 APB 승인을 받기 위해 그의 사무실에 갔을 때 ,
he kept hitting me on the back of the head,
그 사람이 계속 내 뒤통수를 때렸어요
asking how we'll catch the killer with this alone.
이것만으로 범인을 어떻게 잡을 수 있느냐고 묻는다 .
I'm almost 50 now.
저는 이제 거의 50세가 되었습니다.
Gosh. He just can't quit that habit of his, can he?
이런. 그 사람은 그 습관을 그만둘 수 없잖아요 , 그렇죠?
I stayed up all night and managed to persuade the commissioner,
밤을 새워 국장을 설득했는데,
but what will happen to us if this doesn't work?
하지만 이것이 작동하지 않으면 우리는 어떻게 될까요 ?
Well, it can't be undone now.
이제 취소할 수 없습니다.
Don't be scared.
겁먹지 마세요.
Let's wait and see what happens.
무슨 일이 일어나는지 기다려 봅시다.
The reporters are getting a thrill out of this.
이에 기자들은 큰 감동을 받고 있다.
They're watching us with their eyes peeled to see if we'll catch him
그들은 우리가 그를 잡을 수 있는지 눈을 뜨고 우리를 지켜보고 있습니다.
with this photo that shows nothing but his back.
그의 뒷모습만 보이는 이 사진과 함께 .
Come on, Chief Heo. Why are you being like this?
자, 허과장님. 너 왜 이렇게 굴어?
Are you suddenly regretting your decision?
갑자기 결정을 후회하고 있나요?
No, it's not that. I'm just frustrated. That's all.
아니요, 그게 아닙니다. 나는 단지 좌절감을 느낀다. 그게 다야.
It'd be amazing if we could catch that scumbag with this,
이걸로 그 쓰레기 놈을 잡을 수 있다면 정말 좋을 텐데 .
but it's also true it's more important to prevent more murders.
하지만 더 많은 살인을 예방하는 것이 더 중요한 것도 사실입니다 .
You're right.
네가 옳아.
I already let him hit me in the head as if I were his punching bag.
나는 이미 내가 그의 샌드백인 것처럼 그가 내 머리를 때리는 것을 허락했다 .
I don't care if I'm on the chopping block.
내가 도마 위에 있어도 상관없습니다.
-Let's go. -Okay, let's go.
-갑시다. -좋아, 가자.
I came to the right place.
나는 올바른 장소에 왔습니다.
Aren't you from Gangnam Police Station? Wait.
강남경찰서 출신이 아니신가요 ? 기다리다.
Was it Jongno Station?
종로역이었나?
You are a detective, right? Oh, you must be from Seoul HQ.
당신은 탐정이군요, 그렇죠? 아, 서울본부 출신이시군요.
Hello, I'm Reporter Choi Yoon-ji from Fact Today.
안녕하세요, 팩트투데이 최윤지 기자입니다 .
I have your business card.
나는 당신의 명함을 가지고 있습니다.
I knew it. We've met before, right?
알고 있었어. 우리 전에 만난 적 있죠?
Yes, Director.
예, 국장님.
I'm finally getting an exclusive report.
드디어 독점 보고서를 받게 됐습니다.
You're interfering with official police duty.
당신은 공식적인 경찰 업무를 방해하고 있습니다.
-What the heck? -Stop her.
-이런 젠장? - 그만둬요.
There's no exclusive here.
여기에는 독점이 없습니다.
What nonsense are you saying?
무슨 말도 안되는 소리를하고 있습니까?
Let me…
놔줘???
You're the cop who took my phone in front of the motel.
모텔 앞에서 내 전화기를 가져간 경찰이 바로 당신이에요 .
You are that cop, right? My gosh.
당신이 그 경찰 맞죠? 이럴수가.
Goodness.
선량.
Detective, could you spare me a moment?
형사님, 잠시만 시간을 내주실 수 있나요?
I have many questions about this case.
이 사건에 대해 궁금한 점이 많습니다.
The main road is over there.
주요 도로는 저기에 있습니다.
And this is the only security footage of him.
그리고 이것은 그의 유일한 보안 영상입니다.
I just think it's odd.
그냥 이상한 것 같아요.
You put out an APB on a faceless suspect.
얼굴 없는 용의자에게 APB를 발사했습니다.
I don't get it.
이해가 안 돼요.
I can't tell you anything as we're still investigating the case.
아직 사건을 조사하는 중이라 말씀드릴 수 있는 게 없습니다 .
Wait, Detective!
잠깐만요, 형사님!
Can you at least tell me your name if I can't have your number?
제가 당신의 전화번호를 알 수 없다면 최소한 당신의 이름이라도 알려주실 수 있나요 ?
He's leaving like that? What a petty jerk.
그 사람이 그렇게 떠나는 거야? 정말 사소한 바보입니다.
That car…
저 자동차???
SEOUL METROPOLITAN POLICE AGENCY
서울지방경찰청
SERIAL MURDER GAME? WARNING TO SOCIETY OR TO POLICE?
연쇄 살인 게임? 사회에 경고하는가, 아니면 경찰에 경고하는가?
Kim Bong-sik, this jerk!
김봉식 이놈아!
-That's it. -Nice shot.
-그게 다야. -좋은 슛이군요.
MURDER SUSPECT WANTED REWARD 50 MILLION WON
살인 용의자 수배 포상금 5천만원
Darn it, this punk…
젠장, 이 새끼야???
FACELESS SERIAL MURDER SUSPECT
얼굴 없는 연쇄 살인 용의자
What's the map for?
지도는 무엇을 위한 것인가요?
I want to carry it around with me
가지고 다니고 싶어요
when I visit the scenes for profiling purposes.
프로파일링 목적으로 현장을 방문할 때 .
If I mark all the major bus and subway routes
주요 버스, 지하철 노선을 모두 표시하면
and note the time of each incident and even the weather that day,
각 사건의 시간 과 그날의 날씨까지 기록해 두세요.
it'll be helpful.
도움이 될 거예요.
Then I'll help you.
그럼 내가 도와줄게.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
Hey, that's a lot of work.
정말 힘든 일이군요.
I'm stating the obvious,
나는 분명한 사실을 말하고 있다.
but the answers are always found at the scene.
하지만 답은 언제나 현장에서 찾을 수 있습니다.
Shall I make you one too?
나도 하나 만들어 드릴까요?
No, it's okay. We'll share it.
아니 괜찮아. 공유해드리겠습니다.
13 DAYS SINCE THE OPEN SEARCH BEGAN
공개 검색이 시작된 지 13일
NOVEMBER 13, 2003
2003년 11월 13일
GUNGOK-DONG, HWANGHWA-DONG
궁곡동, 황화동
From here…
여기에서???
It means he frequents this area via public transportation.
대중교통을 이용해 이 지역을 자주 오간다는 뜻이다 .
All four cases
네 가지 경우 모두
happened between 10 a.m. and 2 p.m.
오전 10시부터 오후 2시 사이에 발생
A timeframe when it's likely to find only women or the elderly at home.
집에 여성이나 노인들만 있을 가능성이 높은 기간
MEDICAL BOOKS
의학서적
Are you looking for a particular book?
특정 책을 찾고 계십니까?
I'm looking for a book on anatomy.
나는 해부학에 관한 책을 찾고 있어요.
I see. This way, please.
알겠어요. 이쪽으로 오십시오.
You can find them here.
여기서 찾을 수 있습니다.
If you have a particular title you're looking for,
원하시는 특정 타이틀이 있으시면 ,
I can look it up for you.
제가 대신 찾아드릴 수 있습니다.
HUMAN ANATOMY
인체 해부학
ANATOMY
해부학
It's already been over a month since you put out an APB.
APB를 내놓은 지 벌써 한 달이 넘었습니다 .
You still don't have anything for us?
아직 우리한테 줄 게 아무것도 없나요?
At least tell us your lead.
최소한 당신의 단서를 말해주세요.
Well, thankfully there hasn't been another victim yet.
다행히 아직까지 추가 피해자는 발생하지 않았습니다.
We are doing everything we can.
우리는 최선을 다하고 있습니다.
You have to give us something
당신은 우리에게 뭔가를 주어야합니다
so we can write an article.
그래서 우리는 기사를 쓸 수 있어요.
Even after you put out the APB…
APB를 꺼낸 후에도???
-At least share the information! -Tell us anything.
-적어도 정보는 공유해주세요! -무엇이든 말해 보세요.
Come on! Give me something to write about!
어서 해봐요! 나에게 쓸 내용을 주세요!
-Give us information. -Tell us!
-정보를 주세요. -말해보세요!
Why won't you tell us?
왜 우리에게 말하지 않는 거죠?
Please raise your hand and speak one at a time.
손을 들고 한 명씩 말씀해 주십시오.
PROFILING REPORT
프로파일링 보고서
I don't think now is the right time to hand this over.
지금은 이 일을 넘겨줄 때가 아닌 것 같아요 .
I know that too.
나도 그걸 알아요.
I just think they really need a lead.
내 생각엔 그들에게 단서가 정말 필요하다고 생각해요.
I feel like there is a need
필요성이 있다고 느껴지네요
to examine and analyze the culprit's behavior
범인의 행동을 조사하고 분석하기 위해
as much as we can. Now more than ever.
우리가 할 수 있는 만큼. 이제 그 어느 때보다.
It says here…
여기라고 써있나요???
"Effort in trying to steal valuables is very low."
"귀중품을 훔치려는 노력은 매우 낮습니다."
What does this mean?
이것은 무엇을 의미 하는가?
In the case of Hwanghwa-dong, there was an attempt to try to open the safe.
황화동의 경우 금고를 열려고 시도한 경우도 있었다.
If stealing the valuables was his purpose,
귀중품을 훔치는 것이 목적이라면,
it only makes sense to kill the victim after he's made them open the safe.
피해자가 금고를 열도록 한 후에 피해자를 죽이는 것이 합리적입니다 .
But he did the opposite.
그러나 그는 그 반대를 했습니다.
Above that, it says, "Character disorder severe enough
그 위에는 "성격장애가 충분히 심각하다" 고 적혀 있다.
to commit a crime. Highly likely he had issues with family members."
범죄를 저지르려고. 가족들과 문제가 있었을 가능성이 높다 ”고 말했다.
Even if we can get his medical history, how can we know if he has issues at home?
설사 그의 병력을 알 수 있다고 하더라도 그가 집에 문제가 있는지 어떻게 알 수 있습니까?
For a person with this much rage,
이 정도 분노를 갖고 있는 사람에게는
I'm sure that it showed in his daily life too.
나는 그것이 그의 일상생활에서도 드러났을 것이라고 확신한다 .
We can't take a survey of every household though.
하지만 모든 가구를 대상으로 설문조사를 실시할 수는 없습니다 .
It's not like we can ask
우리가 물어볼 수 있는 게 아니잖아
if they have a family member who has a lot of anger.
가족 중에 화를 많이 내는 사람 이 있다면 .
By the way, where is Chief Kim Bong-sik?
그런데 김봉식 과장은 어디 있나요?
He said he was going to the sauna.
사우나에 간다고 하더군요.
My goodness.
이럴 수가.
Just how much dirt does he need to wash off?
얼마나 많은 먼지를 씻어내야 합니까?
But here, it says, "The culprit's crimes,
그런데 여기에는 "범인의 범죄,
planning, and choice of location and time are too systematic.
계획, 장소 및 시간 선택이 너무 체계적입니다.
It's unlikely that he has an intellectual disability or schizophrenia.
지적 장애나 정신분열증이 있을 가능성은 거의 없습니다 .
Therefore, there is a need to focus the investigation on people
그러므로 사람에 대한 수사에 집중할 필요가 있다.
who have an aggressive character disorder."
공격적인 성격장애를 갖고 있는 사람."
I'm having trouble understanding this part.
이 부분을 이해하는데 어려움을 겪고 있습니다 .
What's the reason we have to differentiate
차별화를 해야하는 이유가 무엇인가요?
schizophrenia, intellectual disabilities, and character disorders?
정신분열증, 지적 장애, 성격 장애?
Character disorder is an illness when one shows extreme
성격장애는 극단적인 모습을 보일 때 나타나는 질병이다.
or deformed forms of obsessive dependent, avoidant,
또는 기형적인 형태의 강박적 의존, 회피,
or antisocial characteristics.
또는 반사회적 특성.
But everyone makes little of this illness
하지만 모두가 이 병에 대해 별로 개의치 ​​않습니다.
so they don't take active measures to treat it.
그래서 그들은 그것을 치료하기 위해 적극적인 조치를 취하지 않습니다 .
So there may not be medical records of it then.
그렇다면 의료 기록이 없을 수도 있습니다 .
Yes, that's right.
네, 맞습니다.
Even if he did get treatment,
치료를 받았음에도 불구하고
it probably didn't last long.
아마도 오래 가지 않았을 것입니다.
The possibility of having been admitted to a closed ward
폐쇄병동에 입원 했을 가능성
is extremely low too.
매우 낮습니다.
Meaning character disorders don't leave many clues.
성격 장애는 많은 단서를 남기지 않는다는 의미입니다.
Are you sure it's not someone with an intellectual disorder or schizophrenia?
지적 장애나 정신분열증을 앓고 있는 사람이 아닌 것이 확실합니까 ?
All right.
괜찮은.
Let me explain this to you easily.
이것을 쉽게 설명하겠습니다.
Patients with schizophrenia, intellectual disorder, or delusion.
정신분열증, 지적장애, 망상이 있는 환자 .
It's hard for them to commit premeditated crimes.
계획적인 범죄를 저지르는 것은 어렵습니다 .
You saw the crime scene of this case.
이 사건의 범죄현장을 보셨군요.
It's clean and there's no witness.
깨끗하고 증인도 없습니다.
You're right. Cho Hyun Gil wasn't mentally ill either.
네가 옳아. 조현길 역시 정신병이 아니었다.
What we're trying to tell you is
우리가 당신에게 말하려는 것은
instead of mental patients who have been receiving continuous treatment,
지속적인 치료를 받아온 정신질환자 대신
although the chances are low,
비록 확률은 낮지만,
we should look for a suspect who has a record.
전과가 있는 용의자를 찾아야 해요 .
That's what we mean.
이것이 바로 우리가 의미하는 바입니다.
That means it will be harder to narrow down a suspect.
즉 , 용의자를 좁히기가 더 어려워진다는 뜻이다 .
I thought you said you'd make it easier. I'm more confused now.
당신이 일을 더 쉽게 해줄 거라고 말했던 것 같아요. 지금은 더 혼란스러워요.
That's too broad.
너무 광범위해요.
We don't have enough people as is.
지금처럼 사람이 부족해요.
Based on what you're saying,
말씀하신 내용을 토대로,
every single citizen is a suspect then.
그러면 모든 시민이 용의자입니다.
To be blunt, who doesn't have a temper?
솔직하게 말하면 화를 잘 내지 않는 사람이 어디 있겠습니까?
Besides our benevolent Superintendent Baek.
우리 자애로운 백 교육감 외에.
So these are more or less just guesswork.
그래서 이것들은 어느 정도 추측일 뿐입니다.
Right?
오른쪽?
It's not like you gave us a specific lead that we can investigate on.
우리가 조사할 수 있는 구체적인 단서를 제공한 것은 아닙니다 .
We can't mobilize the entire squad just based on this.
이것만으로는 전체 분대를 동원할 수 없습니다 .
It's been over three months
3개월이 넘었습니다
and the police still don't have a single lead on the culprit.
경찰은 아직까지 범인에 대한 단서를 하나도 갖고 있지 않습니다.
He's a murderer who killed seven people.
그는 일곱 사람을 죽인 살인자입니다.
You're talking as if the police are incompetent.
경찰이 무능한 것처럼 말하고 있군요 .
But they are doing their very best.
하지만 그들은 최선을 다하고 있습니다.
That goes for the Hwanghwa-dong case from October too.
10월 황화동 사건도 마찬가지다 .
They found an image of the culprit from CCTV footage.
CCTV 영상에서 범인의 이미지를 발견했습니다 .
Also, they are actively receiving tip-offs
또한 적극적으로 제보를 받고 있습니다
so they will find a lead on the culprit soon.
그래서 그들은 곧 범인에 대한 단서를 찾을 것입니다 .
It's already been over two months since they released an APB.
APB를 출시한 지 벌써 두 달이 넘었습니다 .
If they were relying on the APB for a lead they should've gotten one a long time ago.
APB에 리드를 의존하고 있었다면 오래 전에 APB를 확보했어야 했습니다.
Time is passing, including this moment here.
지금 이 순간을 포함해 시간은 흐르고 있습니다 .
People are growing more anxious by the day.
사람들의 불안은 나날이 증가하고 있습니다 .
What do they plan on doing about this?
이 문제에 대해 무엇을 할 계획인가요?
To strengthen public security
공공 안보 강화
on top of increasing the number of patrolling officers,
순찰관의 수를 늘리는 것 외에도
they have offered many solutions like installing security cameras
보안 카메라 설치와 같은 다양한 솔루션을 제공했습니다
in crime-ridden districts.
범죄가 잦은 지역
They are currently executing those solutions.
현재 해당 솔루션을 실행하고 있습니다 .
DECEMBER 31, 2003
2003년 12월 31일
JANUARY 2, 2004
2004년 1월 2일
SUSEONG-DONG, JINJUNG-DONG
수성동,진중동
Seriously!
진지하게!
-It's already been months! -What is this?
-벌써 몇 달이 지났어요! -이게 뭔가요?
He's a murderer. They only got a picture of his back.
그는 살인자입니다. 그들은 단지 그의 등 사진만을 얻었습니다.
How do they plan to catch him with this?
이걸로 어떻게 그를 잡을 계획인가요?
-Seriously. -That's what I mean!
-진지하게. - 내 말은 바로 그거야!
-How can they catch him? -Seriously.
- 어떻게 그를 잡을 수 있나요? -진지하게.
Gosh, he's an evil one, isn't he?
맙소사, 그 사람은 사악한 사람이지, 그렇지?
-Yes. -You're right.
-예. -네가 옳아.
Why can't they catch him?
왜 그를 잡지 못하는 걸까요?
-What are the police doing? -Exactly.
- 경찰은 뭐하고 있나요? -정확히.
They still haven't been able to catch a punk like this.
그들은 아직 이런 놈을 잡지 못했습니다 .
-I know right? -Yes.
- 알죠? -예.
Next up.
다음입니다.
It's been over three months since the police released
경찰이 석방된 지 3개월이 넘었습니다
an APB with a picture of the suspect's back.
피의자의 뒷모습 사진이 있는 APB
This serial murder case of rich, elderly citizens
부자노인 연쇄살인사건
shocked the nation last October.
지난 10월 전국을 놀라게 했습니다.
They still haven't been able to catch the suspect yet.
아직 용의자를 잡지 못했습니다 .
Inspector Song or whatever is nowhere to be found.
송 경위나 뭐든 찾을 수 없습니다.
I can't find anything.
아무것도 찾을 수 없습니다.
It's been reported to us.
우리에게 보고되었습니다.
Simultaneously, the police continue to look for the suspect…
이와 동시에 경찰은 계속해서 용의자를 찾고 있다???
I don't even know anymore.
나는 더 이상 모른다.
They stated…
그들은???
-I'll write one up quickly. -No, it's fine.
-빨리 하나 쓰겠습니다. -아니요, 괜찮아요.
Captain.
선장.
Take a look at this.
이것 좀 보세요.
The decision for an open search.
공개 검색에 대한 결정
Is this the police's lifeline or is this the beginning of doom?
이것은 경찰의 생명선인가 , 아니면 파멸의 시작인가?
FACT TODAY, REPORTER CHOI YOON-JI
FACT TODAY, 최윤지 기자
If the culprit does not stop
범인이 멈추지 않는다면
and continues to commit the crimes in hiding,
은신처에서 계속해서 범죄를 저지르고 있습니다.
it might turn into a bad move that'll lead to difficulty
어려움을 초래하는 나쁜 움직임으로 변할 수도 있습니다
in finding leads to the culprit.
범인을 찾는 데
The murders broke out four times, not just once.
살인은 한 번이 아닌 네 번이나 발생했습니다.
How can they not catch the culprit?
어떻게 범인을 잡지 않을 수 있나요?
The pathetic reality of the police.
경찰의 한심한 현실
-Just as I expected of the police. -When will they catch the culprit?
-경찰에서 예상했던 대로였습니다. -범인은 언제 잡힐까요?
I'm too scared.
너무 무서워요.
The culprit will definitely kill someone again.
범인은 분명 또 누군가를 죽일 것입니다.
It was too rash to start an open search.
공개 검색을 시작하기에는 너무 성급했습니다.
The culprit would only hide more.
범인은 더 많은 것을 숨길 뿐입니다.
I'd trust my dog before I trust the police.
나는 경찰을 믿기 전에 내 개를 믿을 것입니다.
You wanted to make the Behavioral Analysis Team,
행동분석팀을 만들고 싶었는데 ,
so I let you have your way, but what have you done right?
그래서 네 마음대로 하게 놔뒀는데, 네가 제대로 한 일이 뭐니?
You began an open search just by using a photo of his back,
그의 뒷모습 사진만으로 공개 검색을 시작하셨는데요 ,
but you have no evidence?
그런데 증거가 없나요?
This only made the police look ridiculous!
이것은 경찰을 우스꽝스럽게 보이게 만들었습니다!
How will you patch this up?
이걸 어떻게 패치할 건가요?
Commissioner.
위원.
Our detectives are out there running around and doing their best.
우리 형사들은 여기 저기 뛰어다니며 최선을 다하고 있습니다.
And so is the Behavioral Analysis Team.
행동분석팀도 마찬가지입니다.
I don't want your best!
나는 당신의 최선을 원하지 않습니다!
Bring me the result!
결과를 가져오세요!
Bring that jerk who killed seven people immediately!
7명을 죽인 저 새끼를 당장 데려와라 !
Put him before those wordy reporters!
그 장황한 기자들 앞에 그를 세워라!
When you were out on the field,
현장에 나갔을 때,
you taught us a few ways, and we tried everything.
당신은 우리에게 몇 가지 방법을 가르쳐 주었고 우리는 모든 것을 시도했습니다.
We asked around the crime scene,
사건 현장을 둘러보니,
we talked to every deliveryman around the area.
우리는 그 지역의 모든 배달원들과 이야기를 나눴습니다 .
We searched every Internet cafe user in the area.
우리는 해당 지역의 모든 인터넷 카페 사용자를 검색했습니다 .
We even got a warrant to search the base station,
기지국 수색 영장까지 받았어요
and searched every person who used their phones in the area.
그리고 그 지역에서 휴대전화를 사용하는 모든 사람을 수색했습니다.
But we still haven't found a strand of the culprit's hair.
하지만 아직까지 범인의 머리카락 한 가닥도 찾지 못했습니다 .
The Behavioral Analysis Team or whoever, we need to ask
행동분석팀 이든 누구에게든 물어봐야 합니다
and find a new method
그리고 새로운 방법을 찾아보세요
of investigating this case.
이 사건을 조사하는 중입니다.
Yes, so just as the Analysis Team reported on the profiling report,
네, 그럼 분석팀이 프로파일링 보고서에서 보고한 것처럼 ,
we plan on searching for people with mental illnesses
우리는 정신 질환이 있는 사람들을 찾을 계획입니다
who have sought help along with the investigation.
조사와 함께 도움을 구한 사람 .
Darn it.
젠장.
You didn't know that I've been getting reports
내가 보고를 받고 있다는 걸 넌 몰랐지?
that the Analysis Team is out on the field, did you?
분석팀이 현장에 나가 있다고 했죠?
-Sorry? -They keep asking me
-죄송합니다? - 계속 나한테 물어보는데
who those guys are and complaining about them.
그 사람들은 누구이고 그들에 대해 불평합니다.
I can only turn a blind eye to those complaints for so long.
나는 오랫동안 그러한 불만을 무시할 수밖에 없었습니다 .
We can't force them to stop when they want to take part
그들이 참여하고 싶을 때 멈추도록 강요할 수는 없습니다.
in the investigation.
조사 중.
Enough.
충분한.
I don't want to hear your excuses anymore.
더 이상 당신의 변명을 듣고 싶지 않습니다.
Make sure you take firm measures.
확고한 조치를 취하시기 바랍니다.
-Yes, sir.
-알겠습니다.
What is it you want to say?
무슨 말을 하고 싶은 걸까요?
What is it?
그것은 무엇입니까?
Let's put an end to our obsession.
집착을 끝내자.
The SCS has too many cases to resolve
SCS에 해결해야 할 사례가 너무 많습니다.
rather than look for some guy who can't even be detected.
들키지도 않는 남자를 찾는 것보다 .
You talk as if we're a huge burden to the Special Crime Squad.
마치 우리가 특수수사대에 큰 부담이 되는 것처럼 말하는군요 .
You never even bother to hear us out.
당신은 우리의 말을 듣는 데 전혀 신경 쓰지 않습니다.
Young-soo, that's not what happened.
영수씨, 그런 일이 아니었어요.
We began an open search for him just with a photo of his back.
우리는 그의 뒷모습 사진만으로 그를 찾기 시작했습니다 .
The commissioner taught me a big lesson when I went in
내가 들어갔을 때 위원님이 나에게 큰 교훈을 가르쳐 주셨다.
to have some documents approved.
일부 문서를 승인받으려면
-So you called us to nitpick over that? -Nitpick? I'm your superior.
-그래서 그 문제에 대해 트집을 잡으려고 우리를 불렀나요? -니픽? 나는 당신의 상사입니다.
Why would I do that with you two?
내가 왜 너희 둘한테 그런 짓을 하겠어?
If anything, I'd give you an order.
그렇다면 나는 당신에게 명령을 내릴 것입니다.
All I'm saying is that we've all done enough.
제가 말씀드리고 싶은 것은 우리 모두 할 만큼 했다는 것입니다.
What do you mean by enough? Are you telling us to give up?
충분하다은 무슨 뜻인가요? 우리한테 포기하라고 말하는 거야?
Hey, there is no giving up when it comes to our cases.
안녕하세요, 우리의 경우에는 포기란 없습니다 .
I'm saying there are many cases we could solve with that time.
그 시간이면 해결할 수 있는 사건이 많다고 하더군요 .
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
We never just sat on our hands.
우리는 결코 손을 놓고 앉아 있지 않았습니다.
The Behavioral Analysis Team has done our duty by ourselves.
행동분석팀은 스스로 임무를 수행했습니다.
What is it? Stop beating around the bush and tell me.
그것은 무엇입니까? 수풀 주위를 두드리는 것을 멈추고 나에게 말하십시오.
Goodness.
선량.
I'll be frank.
솔직하게 말할게요.
Those up above aren't happy
위에 있는 사람들은 행복하지 않아요
with the Behavioral Analysis Team.
행동분석팀과 함께합니다.
They were never happy with us. Good grief.
그들은 결코 우리에게 만족하지 않았습니다. 맙소사.
We're a workplace. An organization. What can we do?
우리는 직장입니다. 조직. 우리는 무엇을 할 수 있나요?
Those men out there also are complaining
저 밖에 있는 남자들도 불평하고 있어
about how your team is coming in and out of the crime scenes.
당신의 팀이 범죄 현장에 어떻게 들어오고 나가는지에 대해 .
The only thing we can do is investigate the crime scene.
우리가 할 수 있는 유일한 일은 범죄 현장을 조사하는 것뿐이다.
-If you stop us from doing that… -I mean,
-우리가 그러지 못하게 하면??? -내 말은,
I just want to stop by the crime scene after the forensics are done.
법의학 조사가 끝난 후 범죄 현장에 들러보고 싶습니다 .
What's the problem?
뭐가 문제 야?
There are many other things you can work on.
당신이 할 수 있는 다른 일들이 많이 있습니다 .
You know, those documents you took from the cabinets.
당신 이 캐비닛에서 가져온 그 문서를 알고 있습니다 .
You all study that and create data too.
여러분도 그걸 연구해서 데이터를 만드세요.
That's our job, so we'll manage, okay?
그게 우리 일이니까 우리가 알아서 할게, 알았지?
Please don't stop us from going to the crime scenes.
우리가 범죄 현장에 가는 것을 막지 마십시오 .
There's nothing he can do to stop us. We can go whenever we want to.
그가 우리를 막기 위해 할 수 있는 일은 아무것도 없습니다. 우리는 원할 때 언제든지 갈 수 있어요.
Forget it. I'm done with this. Goodbye.
잊어 버려. 이제 끝났습니다. 안녕히 가세요.
We need to put an end to this. Inspector Song.
우리는 이것을 끝내야 합니다. 송 검사님.
I know you visit the crime scene every day.
나는 당신이 매일 범죄 현장을 방문하는 것을 알고 있습니다.
I'm not trying to stop you.
나는 당신을 막으려는 것이 아닙니다.
Please use your effort on something else too.
다른 일에도 힘쓰시기 바랍니다 .
Let's go.
갑시다.
I'm talking to him right now.
나는 지금 그 사람과 이야기하고 있습니다.
It's my first time having a serious talk with him.
그 사람과 진지하게 대화를 나누는 건 처음이에요 .
You don't have to listen. There's nothing serious about it.
들을 필요는 없습니다. 그것에 대해 심각한 것은 없습니다.
Come on out.
나오세요.
That little…
그 작은???
Please excuse me.
실례합니다.
You understand what I mean, right?
무슨 말인지 이해하시겠죠?
-What now? -What do you mean?
- 지금은요? -무슨 뜻이에요?
I would've never started if I was going to stop.
멈출 생각이었다면 절대 시작하지 않았을 거예요 .
Do you know something we have in common?
우리 공통점이 뭔지 아세요?
-Nothing. -Exactly.
-아무것도 아님. -정확히.
Who do they think we are?
그들은 우리가 누구라고 생각하나요?
Let's not lose our spirit. We have lots to do.
정신을 잃지 말자. 우리는 할 일이 많습니다.
Mr. Gu Young-chun, please come on in.
구영춘 씨, 들어오세요.
X-RAY ROOM
엑스레이실
Sir, we're about to take an X-ray of your entire body.
선생님, 이제 곧 전신 엑스레이를 찍을 예정입니다 .
64 DAYS SINCE THE OPEN SEARCH BEGAN
공개 검색이 시작된 지 64일
JANUARY 3, 2004
2004년 1월 3일
Did he give up on committing another crime to hide?
그는 숨기기 위해 또 다른 범죄를 저지르기를 포기한 걸까요 ?
Or…
아니면???
is he still planning another crime?
아직도 또 다른 범죄를 계획하고 있나요?
You never miss a day.
하루도 놓치지 마세요.
We never know when the crimes will start again.
범죄는 언제 다시 시작될지 알 수 없습니다 .
Don't believe…
믿지 못하시나요???
that you decided to begin the open search all by yourself.
당신 이 직접 공개 검색을 시작하기로 결정했다는 것입니다 .
The Special Crime Squad isn't incompetent
특수수사대는 무능하지 않다
to the point we'd blindly follow
우리가 맹목적으로 따라갈 정도로
a rash decision.
성급한 결정.
From the outside,
바깥으로부터,
it may seem like the investigation is standing still.
수사가 정지된 것처럼 보일 수도 있습니다 .
Until the moment we catch the culprit,
범인을 잡는 그 순간까지,
even we sometimes feel that way.
우리도 가끔 그렇게 느낄 때가 있어요.
However,
하지만,
we came to this choice altogether.
우리는 전적으로 이 선택을 하게 되었습니다.
What doesn't change is how we came to the same decision.
변하지 않는 것은 우리가 같은 결정을 내린 방법입니다.
That all we want is to catch the culprit.
우리가 원하는 것은 범인을 잡는 것뿐입니다.
What's more important than wanting to catch the culprit
범인을 잡는 것보다 더 중요한 것은
is actually catching the culprit.
실제로 범인을 잡는 중입니다.
We will catch him. Certainly.
우리는 그를 잡을 것입니다. 틀림없이.
He will not stop.
그는 멈추지 않을 것입니다.
We'll catch him before he goes on.
그가 계속하기 전에 우리는 그를 잡을 것입니다.
I thought it would work once we stopped him.
우리가 그를 막으면 효과가 있을 거라고 생각했어요 .
I look through the daily reports every morning,
매일 아침 일일 보고서를 살펴보는데 ,
and I don't see a report of a crime in that same pattern.
같은 패턴으로 범죄가 보고된 경우는 본 적이 없습니다 .
What if…
만약 그러하다면???
What if the culprit changed the MO?
범인이 MO를 바꾸었다면?
What do we do then?
그러면 우리는 무엇을 합니까?
DAILY CASE REPORT
일일 사례 보고서
JANUARY 30, 2004 VICTIM: KIM YANG-HEE
2004년 1월 30일 피해자 : 김양희
THE VICTIM WAS STABBED WITH A CAMPING KNIFE
피해자는 캠핑용 칼에 찔렸습니다.
-Go home. -See you later.
-집에가. -나중에 봐요.
-Call me. -Text me.
-전화해. -나에게 문자 해.
-Hurry. It's getting cold. -Okay, bye.
-서두르다. 추워지고있다. -괜찮아 안녕.
-Call me.
-전화해.
FEBRUARY 12, 2004
2004년 2월 12일
SINHEUNG 2-DONG, YEONGDEUNGPO-GU
영등포구 신흥2동
Are you home?
집에 계세요?
I'm almost home.
집에 거의 다 왔습니다.
TO SU-MIN
수민에게
The devil has yet again disappeared without a trace.
악마가 또다시 흔적도 없이 사라졌습니다.
Time is ticking.
시간이 흐르고 있습니다.
If this becomes a cold case…
이게 미해결 사건이 된다면???
Most murderers like him usually kill for their own pleasure and enjoyment.
그와 같은 대부분의 살인자들은 대개 자신의 즐거움과 즐거움을 위해 살인을 합니다.
It means killing makes them happy.
살인이 그들을 행복하게 만든다는 뜻입니다.
-Camping knife? -Do you think it's the same guy?
-캠핑칼요? -같은 사람인 것 같나요?
It's similar to the guy we're looking for.
우리가 찾고 있는 사람과 비슷해요.
The murder weapon, MO, and time don't match at all.
살인무기와 MO, 시간이 전혀 일치하지 않습니다.
What if it's what we speculated?
우리가 추측한 대로라면 어떻게 되나요?
What if he failed to finish the job?
그가 일을 마치지 못하면 어떻게 되나요?
Then we have two serial killers in this country.
그렇다면 이 나라에는 두 명의 연쇄 살인범이 있습니다 .